Lorenzo Johnston Greene Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
- Public Interest Organizations, 1931-1988 (Box 76-91)
  - Missouri Advisory Committee to the United States Commission on Civil Rights
    - Background material, 1959-1970, undated
    - Conferences
      - Miscellaneous, 1959-1971
      - Southwestern Title IV conference, 1965
    - Education Subcommittee, 1958-1961, undated
      - Correspondence, 1958-1961, undated
      - Miscellaneous, 1959-1964, undated (Box 78)
      - Questionnaires and related material, 1965, undated
      - Reports and statements
        - Miscellaneous, 1958-1960, undated
        - Report to the United States Commission on Civil Rights on Desegregation of Schools in Missouri by the Missouri Advisory Committee, 1959
    - General Correspondence, 1958-1982, undated, (2 folders)
    - Handbooks, 1958 (Box 79)
    - Housing file, 1958-1970, undated
    - Legislation file, 1964-1965, undated
    - McDonnell-Douglas affirmative action plan, 1970
    - Meetings and hearings, 1958-1971, undated, (2 folders)
    - Members (Box 80)
      - Directories
      - Lists
    - Miscellaneous, 1960, undated
    - Newsletters and releases, 1959-1986, undated
    - Program guide, 1965
    - Publications, 1964-1972, undated
    - Questionnaires and related material, 1959-1962, undated
    - Reports and statements
      - By the United States Commission on Civil Rights, 1959-1971
      - Geographical file (Box 81)
        - Alabama, Illinois, Kansas, 1957-1958, undated
        - Missouri, New York, 1963-1977, undated
        - Tennessee, Wisconsin, 1956-1957, undated
      - Re Indians, 1954, 1960
  - Missouri Association for Social Welfare (MASW)
    - Annual conferences
      - 1939, 1949-1966, (2 folders)
      - 1967-1973, undated (Box 82)
    - Background and historical material, 1964, 1975-1979, 1988, undated
    - Board of directors
      - Correspondence, 1949-1970, 1982, undated, (3 folders)
      - Handbooks and manuals, 1961
      - Meetings
        - 1950-1952, (2 folders)
        - 1953-1961, (5 folders) (Box 83)
        - 1962-1968, undated, (2 folders) (Box 84)
      - Members, 1957-1965, undated
      - Nominating committee, 1951-1974, (2 folders)
      - Reports and statements, 1952-1967, undated
      - Staff file, 1944-1967, 1976, undated
    - Committees
      - Archives Committee, 1974
      - Bylaws Committee, 1948-1962, 1983, undated
      - Civil Rights Committee, 1948
      - Corrections Committee, 1960-1967, 1972
      - Goals Committee, 1976
      - Human Rights Committee
        - Correspondence
          - "A-H" miscellaneous, 1954-1968
          - "J-Y" miscellaneous, 1950-1968, undated (Box 85)
          - Unidentified, 1953, 1968, undated
        - Fair housing file
          - Correspondence, 1956-1968, undated
          - Miscellaneous, 1958, 1966-1968, undated, (2 folders)
        - Meetings, 1949-1968, undated (Box 86)
        - Miscellaneous, 1960-1967, undated
        - Reports and statements, 1952-1967, undated
      - Public Relations Committee, 1954, undated
      - Public Social Services Committee, 1955-1967, undated
      - Welfare of the Aging Committee, 1959, undated
    - Divisions
      - Council on Divisions and Redistricting Committee, 1958
      - East Central Division, 1951-1988, undated
      - Kansas City Area (Jackson Co., Mo.), Northeast, Northwest, Ozark, South Central, Southeast, and Southwest divisions, 1955-1961
      - St. Louis Area Division, 1951-1964, undated
      - West Central Division, 1940-1968, undated
        - Board of Directors, 1953-1968
        - Correspondence, 1940-1966, undated, (2 folders) (Box 87)
        - Membership file, 1953-1966
        - Miscellaneous, 1953-1967, undated
    - General correspondence
      - Brooks, Mary E., 1949-1952
      - "B-W" miscellaneous, 1939-1940, 1952-1986
    - Legislative file
      - Bills, acts, and related material, 1951-1969, undated
      - Correspondence, 1949-1967
      - Directories and lists of legislators, circa 1950-1967
      - Legislative News
        - 1955-1956
        - 1957-1985, (2 folders) (Box 88)
    - Membership drives and fund-raising, 1953-1986, undated
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1950-1970, 1982, undated
    - Missouri Council on Children and Youth
      - Committees
        - Committee for Handicapped Children, 1958
        - Committee on the Problems of Juveniles, 1958-1961
        - Executive Committee, Foster Care Section, 1958-1960, undated
        - Steering Committee, 1958-1961
      - Conferences, 1958, 1967
      - Correspondence, 1951-1954, 1960
      - Miscellaneous, 1951-1959, undated
      - Publications, 1950-1955
      - White House Conference on Youth, 1950-1969, undated (Box 89)
    - Program statements and related material, 1952-1971, undated
    - Publications, 1951-1982, undated
    - Vocational rehabilitation, 1967-1968, undated
  - Missouri Commission for UNESCO, 1946-1957, undated
  - Missouri Commission on Human Rights
    - Bibliographies project, 1969-1970, undated
    - Correspondence, 1959-1987
    - Legislation file, 1984-1985, undated (Box 90)
    - Meetings and conferences, 1959-1987, undated
    - Miscellaneous, undated
    - Newsletters, news releases, and clippings, 1964-1972, undated
    - Reports and related material, 1958-1971, undated
    - A Resource Manual on Affirmative Action in Employment, 1969
    - Textbook evaluation project
  - Missouri Committee for the Humanities, 1981-1985, undated
  - Missouri Council of Churches
    - Christian Life and Work Division, 1958-1960, 1970, undated
    - Executive Board, 1957-1958, 1967-1973
    - General correspondence, 1958-1978
    - Legislation and electoral politics
      - Legislative Digest, 1958-1962, undated
      - Miscellaneous, 1955-1967, undated (Box 91)
    - Miscellaneous, 1955-1959, undated
    - Planning and mission questionnaires, 1968, undated
  - Missouri Legislative Black Caucus, 1983-1985
  - Missouri State Council of Defense, 1943-1944
  - National Urban League
    - Haynes, George E., founder, 1981
    - Miscellaneous, 1971-1973, undated
  - President's Conference on Home Building and Home Ownership, Committee on Negro Housing, 1931
  - Progressive Party of Missouri, 1943, 1948-1950
  - White House Conference on the Minority Aged, 1980-1981, undated
- Speeches and Writings, 1924-1988 (Box 91-101)
  Interviews and panel discussions arranged chronologically; drafts of speeches by Greene arranged alphabetically by title and those by others organized chronologically; drafts and published versions of articles, books, dissertations, diaries, poems, and song lyrics, mostly by Greene, with correspondence, reviews, plans of work, and related material arranged alphabetically by type of material and then by title.
  - Interviews and panel discussions, 1954-1975, undated (Box 91)
  - Speeches
    - By Greene
      - "The Anti-Slavery Movement in New England from 1637 to 1761," undated
      - "Aspects of Black History, 1518-1789," undated
      - "Dr. Carter G. Woodson As I Knew Him," 1987, undated (Box 92)
      - "Free Negroes of Yesterday," undated
      - "Methods of Teaching Teachers to Teach Black History," 1982
      - Miscellaneous speeches, 1934-1986, undated, (2 folders)
      - "The Negro in Colonial New England, 1620-1776," undated
    - By others, 1951-1985, undated
  - Writings
    - Articles and papers
      - By Greene
        - Afro-Americans in Missouri, 1962, undated
        - Afro-Americans in New England during the Colonial and Revolutionary War eras, 1944, 1946, 1961, undated (Box 93)
        - Afro-American soldiers in New England during the Revolutionary War era, 1952, undated
        - Biographical sketches for The Call (Kansas City, Mo.), 1940, undated
        - "Lincoln University's Involvement with the Sharecropper Demonstration in Southeast Missouri 1939-40," 1986-1987
        - "Massacre at Fort Pillow," 1960, undated
        - Miscellaneous articles, 1949-1988, undated
        - "Sidelight on Economic Conditions Among Negroes in the South during the Depression, 1930," 1930-1931, undated
        - "Some Outstanding Black Personalities," undated (Box 94)
      - By others, 1943-1984, undated
    - Books, theses, and dissertations
      - The Abolition of Slavery in New England, 1688-1776
        - Correspondence, 1945-1947
        - Text, undated
      - In Freedom's Birthplace: A Study of Boston Negroes, by John Daniels, introduction by Greene, 1969
      - Missouri's Black Heritage
        - Book, 1979
        - Copy editing file, undated, (2 folders); (1 folder) (Box 95)
        - Correspondence and clippings, 1979-1986, undated
        - Galleys, 1979
        - Manuscript collections bibliography, undated
      - The Negro in Colonial New England, 1620-1776
        - Correspondence, 1941-1980, (4 folders)
        - Miscellaneous, 1941-1969, undated
        - Plans of work and reports, undated
        - Reviews, 1942-1944, undated (Box 96)
        - Text, 1941, (2 folders)
      - The Negro in the Making of Missouri, 1719-1970, circa 1970
      - The Negro in New England, 1620-1776, 1934, 1940, undated
    - Diaries, copy dated 1928, undated
    - Diary transcriptions (Box 97)
      - Fragments, undated, (7 folders); (5 folders) (Box 98)
      - Impressions of the Negro Church in 1928
        - Fragments, undated
        - Reprints, 1951
        - Text, undated, (2 folders); (1 folder) (Box 99)
      - The Negro During the Depression As Seen by an Associate of Dr. Carter G. Woodson, undated, (3 folders)
      - Working with the Founder, Carter G. Woodson, 1928-1930: A Personal Memoir
        - Chapters
          - "Book Selling Odyssey," undated
          - "The Greensville Fiasco," undated
          - "Sidelights on Houston Negroes," undated
          - Introduction by Arvarh E. Strickland, undated
          - Miscellaneous, 1983-1986, undated (Box 100)
          - Text, 1980-1984, (5 folders)
    - Poems
      - By Greene, with related material, 1924-1936, 1973-1981, undated, (2 folders)
      - By others, 1973, undated (Box 101)
    - Song lyrics, 1982
    - Unidentified fragments re Afro-Americans in New England, undated
- Addition, 1705-1985 (Box 101-106)
  Correspondence, photostats of archival documents, topical files, notes, printed matter, and miscellaneous material.
  Organized by type of material or topic.
  Includes two reels of microfilm. Microfilm shelf no. 20,305
  - African American studies, 1984, undated, (2 folders) (Box 101)
  - Correspondence
    - General, 1933-1984, undated, (6 folders)
    - Greene, Thomasina T.
      - Greeting cards, undated, (2 folders)
      - Letters and telegrams (Box 102)
        - 1942-1945, (8 folders)
        - 1946-1947, (5 folders) (Box 103)
        - 1948
          - Jan.-Feb.
          - Mar.-Nov. (Box 104)
        - 1949-1954, undated, (2 folders)
      - Greeting cards, invitations, and thank-you notes, 1944-1952, 1985
  - Greene, Thomasina T.
    - Address book, undated
    - Birth of Lorenzo T. Greene
      - Correspondence
        - Greeting cards, 1952, (2 folders)
        - Letters, 1952 (Box 105)
      - Miscellany, 1952
    - Correspondence, 1933, 1942-1947, 1977
  - Lincoln University, Jefferson City, Mo., 1946-1960, 1971
  - Missouri Advisory Committee to the United States Commission on Civil Rights, 1967-1968
  - Miscellany, 1929, 1943-1965, undated, (2 folders)
  - Printed matter, 1958-1984, (2 folders)
  - Research file
    - Military records
      - Eighteenth United States Colored Infantry Regiment, circa 1863-circa 1865
        Available only on microfilm produced by the National Archives and Records Administration. Shelf no. 20,305, Reel 1
      - Registers of deaths, Missouri volunteer regiments, 1861-1865
        Available only on microfilm produced by the National Archives and Records Administration. Shelf no. 20,305, Reel 2
      - Rhode Island, 1778-1781
    - Miscellany, 1705-1853, 1945-1967, undated, (4 folders) (Box 106)
    - Notes
      - Cards, undated
      - Notebooks, 1958, 1974, undated, (2 folders)
    - Weekly Jefferson Inquirer, Jefferson City, Mo., 1860
  - Scrapbook, circa 1961
  - Talley, Thomas W.
    - Correspondence, 1925, 1946-1952
    - Death and funeral, 1952
    - Miscellany, 1946
  - World War II, ration books and other ephemera, undated
- Oversize, 1863-1964 (Box OV 1-OV 9)
  Charts related to a project tracking references to African-Americans in textbooks and United States Colored Troops muster roll fragments.
  Arranged and described according to the series, containers, and folders from which the items were removed.
  - Academic file (Box OV 1)
    - Research file
      - Afro-Americans
        - Missouri
          - Military units
            - Third Missouri Heavy Artillery Regiment muster roll fragments, 1863 (Container 62)
            - Unidentified muster roll fragments, 1865 (Container 62) (Box OV 2)
        - Textbooks (Box OV 3-OV 9)
          - Chart, circa 1964 (Container 63)